okay I'm going to start this video today
with a story it's the story of gorov so
he's a colleague who came to me the
other day and he's like R I've seen your
videos where you the master class with
Mand on health insurance and life
insurance I understand the fundamentals
but can you go a step further and can
you help me out more and just spoon feed
me the policies that you would recommend
I'm sure you've done your research I'm
sure I trust you can you just please
tell me the policies today is a video
for all the gorov out there if you're a
Goro please drop me a high in the
comments you should watch this video for
3 reasons one you will actually get an
actionable policy by the end of this
video you can go ahead and buy it right
after two you will get tips and tricks
on how to save on premium without
compromising the coverage amount or the
quality of the insurer and three you
will get a spread sheeet at the end of
this video I'm actually going to be
walking you through a spreadsheet which
is my research so I'm going to share all
of that research with you stick with me
three reasons for you to watch please
stay till the end hopefully you'll find
this useful and valuable and share it
with somebody if they are in the market
for a policy this channel is brought to
you by the 01 media Network by zeroda
with their support I'll be helping you
spend your money
wisely okay back to gorov there are six
things that I want to laid out there
before we jump into it one gor wants a
family insurance policy so essentially
he wants to cover himself his wife and
his son 35 352 those are the broad ages
second he doesn't want a policy for his
parents because his parents are already
covered in a separate policy so this
policy will not include them third he
lives in G very important given the Med
medical costs here fourth he wants a
policy which is about a COR in premium
he's not looking to get a small cover he
wants a policy cover which is one cor so
we will be looking at premium policies
that give such coverage fifth he wants
Peace of Mind very important he doesn't
want to save a few thousand rupees right
now in paying premium and then
regretting later if the company doesn't
stand by the promise so he wants
assurance and he wants quality and he
wants peace of mind and he's willing to
spend for it so that's another filter to
keep in mind as you watch this video and
finally uh he has no pre-existing
conditions or any medical conditions and
that's going to have an impact on the
policies we select so with that out of
the way let's jump into it I when when
we did the research I found 30 companies
out there that give health insurance
policy 24 of them are General Insurance
six are health insurance only so like
Ana Star these are only health insurance
companies and then there are general
insurers who give other kind of
insurances as well like in HDFC and so
on so now now the question is how do you
identify which companies to go after
from these 30 companies right for that
you will have to look at my Excel um
here let's let's go through this
together so basically this is these are
the list of all the companies that we
have and there are three different three
different parameters that I've looked at
this data is from irai which is the
insurance regulatory body from December
2024 it's widely available on the
internet I will also share this
spreadsheet through the link in
description so you have this with you
for the rest of the year uh and you can
take care your own decision but I will
tell you what my parameters are right
let's start from column B which is
threeyear claim settlement ratio what
this means is that over the last three
years how many claims were settled by
this company as a percentage of all the
claims that were submitted to them
pretty simple right you want a company
to be sub like making sure that they
stand up to the promise and therefore
they're giving those claims so this is
the definition claims settled upon total
claims averaged over the last 3 years
one quick call out when you go on these
insurance policy websites the numbers
you see that will be much higher because
they are not aggregated over 3 years
they're actually aggregated over a much
shorter time frame to play around with
it right so they're making you bias that
we have very high claim settlement but
you should look at it a longer time
period before we proceed a quick shout
out to today's sponsors ditto it's a
platform I have used personally it's a
happy coincidence that they are also
sponsoring today's video dto spamf free
advice has really helped me in the past
they unbiased they listen to my scenario
and then they recommend a policy that
works for me they're also really good in
terms of their relationships with all of
these companies and so they can help you
with your claims if you so needed later
on all free of cost one feature I really
like about them is that you can chat
with them on WhatsApp for all of the
different queries that you have and it's
spam free you do not need to pull out
your second phone in order to avoid that
spam so go check out ditto link is in
description and thank you ditto for
sponsoring today's video we have all of
these companies here I think needless to
say that the companies right at the
bottom here rahja Navi SRI Chola
mandalam star all of these with like
really bad claim settlement ratios are
out of the picture right G wants
Assurance he wants Peace of Mind these
companies promise anything but that so
I'm going to completely like
controversially even Nea bua care I'm
not going to look at them my criteria is
at least 95% I'm not even going to look
at these 90 percenters I know some of
you could disagree but this is my video
my criteria so that's how it is I'm
going to look at 95% right so that opens
up like with the first filter we are at
about these 11 companies okay next let's
look at this other metric called
incurred claim ratio show this is
another fun metric that I found but
basically what this means is that the
amount of claims paid upon the amount of
premiums collected in a financial year
so if as a company you have collected
premiums worth 100 rupees out of that
100 rupees how much are you actually
giving back to the policy holders in the
form of claims you don't want to be
giving way too much because say if you
are only collecting 100 and giving away
106 hint hint that's taxpayers money so
and that's why you see a new India
Insurance here giving 111% as income
claim ratio they don't even have the 11%
to give so whose money are they giving
they're basically being floated by the
government and again controversial I
would assume they're being floated by
the government but they could have other
loans and other debt I don't know how
it's working out but it's not a good
indicator similarly these other
government company Oriental Insurance
124 that's ridiculous if I were a
shareholder in this company I'd be
really worried um so again I would stay
away from companies that have a really
high incor claim ratio because solvency
becomes a little bit of a challenge
though I'm sure these companies are not
going to go anywhere but again again it
just doesn't give me the comfort so I'd
stay away from these ones which are 100
the other end of the spectrum of incur
claim ratio is companies that are not
giving claims at all and over there if
you look at some companies like look at
this neaa 58% so that's too low that
means they're really like holding back
and they are really trying to make money
here and not giving out claims at all so
this 58% is not a good number either I
think my sweet spot is somewhere around
80 if you're as close to 80 as possible
plus minus 5 10% I think is great uh and
so with that like these pink colored
like baj Allan at 83 aquo 82 Tata AIG at
81 HDFC orgo at 86 SBI at 81 these are
good policies like they they have a
healthy incurred claim ratio and they
are also not overextending themselves
and over stretching themselves by giving
out way too much uh so they should be
solvent there's the third um metric
fourth metric we can look here which is
solvency ratio but I didn't want to look
at it because it's too complicated so
yeah let's keep it simple I am of the
opinion that I'm going to take out all
of these companies here which have
really high claim ratios from the 11
that we chose earlier and we are not
going to look at them right so on incent
claim ratio just rounding out so I'm
basically going to be looking at
companies which are close to around 80 I
think that's the Swit spot that I want
to be around finally there's a lovely
metric called average complaint rate
which is very important I'll tell you
for two reasons one it tells you the
actual numbers in 10,000 claims how many
complaints were submitted to the
regulator to the home Birds man in
insurance and companies are scared of
this because the minute you Lodge a
complaint it gets recorded officially
and then the data is released and then
people like us see that data and make a
decision and that basically impact
future business prospects of these
companies and therefore I think what's
happening here is that you don't want to
be in a company that has a very high
average complaint rate now the industry
average is around 22 out of 10,000 and
so that's like in adya ba which is just
at the average but the lower this is the
better right so the darker the green
shade here it is the better uh New India
Assurance has really low complaint rate
no surprises you're giving out so much
claim why will people be complaining but
it's a good thing that they have a very
low complaint rate HDFC Ergo within the
private sector actually has the least
complaint rate among the policies that
we selected in the first half um so
that's really good we look at others
like adya B has 22 Universal Soo has
about 21 Bajaj Alliance has eight which
is also pretty good so I think it gives
me some confidence that there are some
like Aya BAS just on the edge uh we will
look at adya builda policies um but yeah
just keep in mind that the complaint
that is about at about 22 before I move
forward I also want to say that data
tells only half the story the other half
of the story is going to be in the
comment section and therefore please go
through the comments one see other
people's experience with all of these
policies two if you have an experience
with any of these policies do share them
with the wider Community it'll help
everybody know which policies and how
your experience has been and hopefully
people who are looking for health
insurance polic policies can actually
benefit from that experience sharing
thank you for to those of you who are
actually going to share your experience
okay so those are the companies right
these are the broad companies that we
are looking at now let's get into the
policies of these in addition to these
companies I'm also going to cover Nea
bua and care only because a lot of
agents and advisers are going to be
selling you these policies and therefore
it's important for us to understand
these policies right so now we move on
to the second tab which is policy
remember you have all of this data you
can go through this data in your time
and make sure you make the right
decision so okay let's go through them
the these are the companies and these
are all of the different factors that
we've taken into account right company
I'm not going to SP sweat over but like
one CR cover are they giving a one cor
cover or not New India Assurance doesn't
have a one cor cover from my research it
looks like the maximum they have is 50
lakh rupees so we're not going to be
considering them um you have the details
here if you want to go through it but we
are not going to be considering it next
HDFC Ergo basically all of them have a
one cover except IFCO Tokyo and New
India insurance so that's good number of
cashless hospitals in gur again no
standouts here except I think neaa and
Care actually are on the lower end in
terms of the number of hospitals they
have cashless hospitals one tip here if
you can afford to do reimbursement do
that over cash lless usually hospitals
do not recommend the best treatment and
I learned this from M from labor law um
hospitals are not incentivized to be
recommending the best treatment even if
it falls under your policy if it's a
cash lless and therefore if you have
money in your pocket do reimbursement
and then basically pay the bill on your
own and then claim reimbursement from
the insurance company but but have
anyway looked at because this is a large
one cor policy a lot of these will be
cash less so let's look at Cash less
right so basically all of them seem to
be good on cashless except neaa care uh
and IFCO Tokyo which are slightly on the
lower end of the Spectrum in terms of
the coverage so now next we have this
policy names these are all of the
different policies that we've looked at
there are 15 of them across these
different insurance companies I've
actually looked at multiple policies
from active adya Bill and Tata AIG uh
we'll go through those in great greater
detail but before that what I want to
cover are the different criteria that
I've used to evaluate this and the more
the green here the better basically if
there's a policy that has all greens
that's amazing um and so think of it
this way that the disease sublimit
basically means that what is a different
claim limit for different diseases
straightforward right like if for
example you have a one policy you get a
disease that disease should not have a
separate limit of say 10 lakh Rupees
because then that defeats the purpose of
getting a larger policy so you don't
want a policy that has a sublimit on a
disease next room rent cap you do not
want a policy with any room rent cap you
want the policy to allow you to get any
room that you like uh to make sure that
you can get the treatment that you want
third is copay copay is nothing but like
a sharing of Bill if you go out to eat
you share a bill similarly in copay if
you go to the hospital you don't want to
be sharing your bill with the policy the
policy is supposed to be paying the
entire thing so no copay is preferred
and finally consumables coverage like
ppf kits masks gloves Etc in a lot of
the bills consumables is what is really
really important because it ends ends up
eating into a large portion of the bill
so you want to make sure that your
policy covers for consumables as well
all right finally there's waiting period
existing illness I've not included this
because in Goro's case there are no
existing illnesses so we are not going
to be looking at it but I've left it
here anyway in case you're looking for
it you can do it now let's look at that
what are the policies that are bases
these four criterias what are the
policies that look good first is HDFC
Ergo Optima secure it it is green across
all four boxes looks good digit not good
consumables coverage is not available in
this superare option and then there's
copay which is Zone wise copay might be
applicable Oriental Insurance youth
ecare basic has a room rent cap and does
not include consumables coverage it's
out Tata AIG is an interesting product
they have two Medicare Premier which is
a really premium policy it is a decent
policy it's expensive but it looks like
a decent policy the second one is tataa
how expensive by the way we'll get into
that in a minute but uh both tataa AIG
policies seem pretty decent to me the
Medicare premium Medicare Plus so we
will go through those AO Platinum again
seems like a decent policy we get into
the waiting period but essentially the
Big Value prop of AO Platinum is that
there is zero initial waiting period and
then there is a 0 to four years
pre-existing conditions and zero for
specific illnesses we will cover this in
Greater depth shortly IFCO Tokyo not a
big fan there's a disease sublimit and
there is a room rent cap adya baa again
good on all factors it's green across
Universal Soo has disease sublimit here
so again there are yellows here I'm
going to skip this Bajaj Alliance has a
single private AC room and it's my
Healthcare policy so I'm going to skip
that nea bua I don't like for two
reasons one if you go back you will see
that their claim settlement ratio is in
the early '90s their incurred claim
ratio is really low their complaints are
really high look at this 43 out of
10,000 and 36 out of 10,000 is a really
high rate compared to the industry
averages we want piece of mind we want
Assurance we do not want complaints and
therefore I would not recommend neaa or
care for anybody who can afford a
premium policy right if you're in the
market for a premium policy just stay
away from these Brands is my
recommendation my recommendation I'm no
expert so we looked at these two
policies and even here you need to get
an optional rider for consumables
coverage which is not ideal and IC
lomard this policy called Elevate has a
single private AC room restriction and
needs an optional rider for consumables
coverage so that leaves us with about
four to five policies in terms of the
ones that we can go with HDFC orgo these
Tata AIG and the adya baa policy these
are the ones that we will evaluate in
the next tab before we move there I also
want to cover the premium amounts for
these policies right now the premium
amount for HDFC orgo for one CR for two
PE 35 year olds and one 2 year old is
47,7 189 here's the trick on how you can
save on this premium one big feature of
HDFC aggo is that you get 2x coverage
from day one which means that if your
coverage is 50 lakh rupees from day one
you get a 1 Premium that's a great thing
because now you can actually buy a 50
lakh rupee cover which cost you $ 4,959
and you're covered for 1 the second
thing is that is this concept of
aggregate deductible what that means is
and I have said this repeatedly and I'm
going to say it again some of you might
disagree but the way I think of health
insurance is that smaller expenses like
2 lakh three lakh even 5 lakhs is not
going to break your back it's the larger
expenses that are going to lead to
financial ruin and therefore I
personally believe that taking an
aggregate deductible is not a bad thing
take it till you can afford it a couple
of lcks here and there is not going to
make a big difference and so take a
aggregate deductible of say 2 lakh
rupees and that would really bring down
your uh policy amount the cover amount
to like from 4,959 it comes down to
24,576 which is crazy just because you
added an aggregate deductible there HDFC
orgo allows for an aggregate deductible
not all policies allow for it so the
trick is get an aggregate deductible if
your policy allows for it for 1 lakh 2
lakhs whatever and save more premium on
it right so technically we get to about
a premium for HDFC orgo at 24,576 Optima
secure next digit we not evaluating but
this is the price tataa AIG this is the
other one Medicare Premier which we
spoke about I'm going to freeze this
column okay I'm going to hide these two
columns um so now let's get to HDFC
Premier Medicare premium I told you this
is an expensive policy 54,6 18 is the
premium for this quite expensive it has
a deductible of 50 K so if you add that
50k deductible 54618 becomes 5286 the
other notes here are that 50 lakhs per
year renewal bonuses there up to a Max
of one CR it has worldwide coverage this
is one of the few policies that gives
you worldwide coverage it has a great
restoration benefit I do not want to get
into restoration benefit get too complex
but check it out if you're interested
and it has bariatric and maternity
covered again things that most other the
policies are not going to give you so
this seems to be like the absolute
cremel in terms of the features it's
giving you but it's also fairly
expensive so if if it suits your if it
suits your purpose go for it the policy
wordings are also here as by the way as
a part of my research I actually put a
lot of the health document policies here
in Notebook LM you can see the screen
here uh you should check it out is
notebook lm. google.com you can upload
policy wordings and then you can start
asking questions from notebook LM you
can make a podcast here and then you can
hear them talk about the policies you
can ask questions it's super fun never
did anybody say policies are super fun
but any anyway getting back to this
right so uh yeah that's there then we
have Medicare plus this is a lower
variant of Medicare Premier uh the
premium is also much lower it's 24655 if
you put a three L deductible the premium
becomes
21352 no restoration benefit is the
problem with this one but worldwide
coverage is there so ACO Platinum very
popular policy very cheap 2,458 for 235
year old and one 2year old uh for the
year aggregate deductible is not
available in this one so basically you
are covered from zero rupees the only
thing in this is that they do not give
it to everybody they will get a medical
test done for you before they give you
this policy if they don't if you don't
qualify for it then they will not give
you this policy adya B has two adya one
active one next and active One Max Key
difference between this is that Max
gives a bonus of 100% on renewal up to
5x and Max has a 2X cover benefit so
again you can take a call on these two I
personally am not a big fan of AD B I
will cover that shortly but my reason
for that is this 22 is not a good enough
number I will why will I pay 38,000 here
to get either of these policies and not
instead get an HDFC or go at 24,576 when
it's meeting my purpose right it serves
my purpose I would go for that as
opposed to these so therefore the
shortlisted policies for now are here
right just to make your life simple this
is the last tab I promise but the
shortlisted policies here are there is
HDFC orgo there is Tata AIG Medicare
premium Medicare plus ACO platinum and
active 1 and active One Max you can get
any of these policies they're all pretty
decent the only thing I want to call out
is two caveats one in fact let's go one
by one for each policy right HDFC Ergo
is a general insurance company they do
not have too many options Optima secure
seems to be a good policy matches all
our boxes that we want to do it
basically is has everything that we need
uh existing illness cover is three years
if any of you have it in our case we're
not looking at that as a criteria so we
don't really care much with a one lakh
deductible the premium is
24,576 uh which is pretty compelling and
yeah that's my personal choice is Optima
secure out of all of these Tata AIG
Medicare Premier and plus both seem okay
to me I don't see much of a difference
they both give the restoration benefit
is not then in plus but I think they're
both pretty decent one thing to look out
for is that when you look at Tata aigs
this year claim ratio like the last
threee claim ratio 96% but if you look
at the year prior if you remove the
immediate last year 2024 and you look at
21 22 23 then this claim ratio is
actually much lower so that's something
to keep in mind that there's a little
bit of a recency bias here but if you
are okay with that I think you can you
can do this if there are any people in
the comments who can leave their
experience on Tata AIG that would be
super helpful AO Platinum I just want to
point your attention to this one little
snippet that I found I think I found
this on ao's website or on ditto I don't
know but essentially what we're saying
is that to be eligible your family must
go through detailed Health tests in a
lab to detect and valuate any
pre-existing health conditions and if
you have any of those then we will offer
you the standard Health Plan and not the
Platinum health plan so that's something
that you should keep in mind as you
evaluate AO but otherwise it's not bad
last adya B one thing I found out here
was that the aggregate deductible cover
is only on the Thea website so you have
to go sign up on the website and then do
it so that's where we're at I have the
HDFC Oro Optima secure I'm happy with it
but here are some other policies you can
consider so that brings us to the end of
today's video hope you found that useful
if you want that spreadsheet that I just
presented just follow the link in
description go to my newsletter sign up
and I will send it to you it's for free
you just need to sign up for it gorov I
hope you got your answer if you didn't
and if your scenario varies from what
gor's is you know who to call ditto they
are spam free they are unbiased you can
get to schedule a call with them or chat
to them on WhatsApp and they help you
with your claims all free of cost I have
personally used them I would highly
recommend them also a quick caveat while
ditto sponsored the video then show for
policies that are recommended are based
my research dto has no role to play
there they are not influencing those
policies in any way I just want to call
it out lastly please drop a comment if
you have any of these policies if you
have an experience with them data tells
only half the story I want to make sure
that the qualitative aspect of these
policies is well captured for all of
those who are viewing this I would
highly encourage you to please drop a
comment about your experiences with
these policies thank you see you in the
next one bye-bye